Robert C. Graham
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Robert C. Graham collection of artists' letters
1783-1935 (bulk 1804-1877)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Graham, Robert Claverhouse
40 items
The Robert C. Graham collection of forty artists' letters dates from 1783 to 1935, with the bulk of the letters dating from 1804 to 1877. Graham, an art dealer and collector, compiled the unrelated letters of several late eighteenth-century and nineteenth-century painters such as Thomas Biddle, Thomas Doughty, G. P. A. Healy, Daniel Huntington, Henry Inman, Emanuel Leutze, Samuel F. B. Morse, Rembrandt Peale, John Singer Sargent, Thomas Sully, John Trumbull, Benjamin West, and others.
Biographical Note
Robert Claverhouse Graham (1913-1994) was the director of the Graham Gallery in New York City. He and his brother James were fourth generation owners of the gallery which specialized in nineteenth- and twentieth-century American art.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert C. Graham collection of forty artists' letters dates from 1783 to 1935, with the bulk of the letters dating from 1804 to 1877. Graham, an art dealer and collector, compiled the unrelated letters of several late eighteenth-century and nineteenth-century painters such as Thomas Doughty, G. P. A. Healy, Daniel Huntington, Henry Inman, Emanuel Leutze, Samuel F. B. Morse, Rembrandt Peale, John Singer Sargent, Thomas Sully, John Trumbull, Benjamin West, and others.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by the author of the letter. Multiple letters within folders are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Related material found in the Archives includes the recording and transcript of a 1976 interview of Robert Claverhouse Graham conducted by Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art. The Archives also holds numerous collections of papers related to or created by the artists who wrote these letters.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art dealers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- 19th century; Artists' writings
Types of Materials:
Letters
Names:
Doughty, Thomas, 1793-1856; Healy, G. P. A. (George Peter Alexander), 1813-1894; Huntington, Daniel, 1816-1906; Inman, Henry, 1801-1846; Leutze, Emanuel, 1816-1868; Morse, Samuel Finley, 1791-1872; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872; Trumbull, John, 1756-1843; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1961 by Robert C. Graham.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Robert C. Graham Collection of Artists' Letters, circa 1783 - circa 1935, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Robert Graham's collection of forty artist's letters includes letters to and from numerous significant American artists, primarily from the mid- to late- nineteenth century. Found are letters from John Brown, Thomas Biddle, Thomas Doughty, G. P. A. Healy, Daniel Huntington, Henry Inman, Emanuel Leutze, Samuel F. B. Morse, Rembrandt Peale, Luigi Persico, John Singer Sargent, Benjamin West, Joseph Wood, and other artists.
  The letters discuss a wide variety of unrelated scattered topics, but are primarily about current work and commissions. Items of note include three letters from Thomas Doughty and one letter from William M. Hart, both Hudson River School painters, to Uriah Levison, discussing paintings Levison commissioned from them. Also found is a letter from sculptor Luigi Persico to the Library of Congress concerning a possible commission for an equestrian statue of George Washington. Letters from Rembrandt Peale concern a portrait of George Washington, and a letter from Thomas Sully to Asher B. Durand requests etchings of two paintings. Also of note are letters from artist John Trumbull, including one to Andrew Robertson in which he discusses many general issues such as the British economy's effect on arts patronage and the engraving of one of his paintings. The collection contains three letters from Benjamin West, including a letter from West to Charles Willson Peale in which he inquires about a painting of George Washington, and a letter to Trumbull congratulating him on the opening of an "Academy of Art."
  The collection contains a few additional items, including an engraved bookplate signed by John Callender, receipts signed by Francis Bicknell Carpenter and William Miller, Thomas Biddle's stock certificate for a share in the Philadelphia Academy of the Fine Arts, and G. P. A. Healy's portrait price list.
  - Biddle, Thomas, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brown, John H., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Callender, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carpenter, Francis Bicknell, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clark, Aaron, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Doughty, Thomas, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dreer, Ferdinand J., 1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Durand, John, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hart, William M., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Healy, G. P. A., 1857-1873 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hinshelwood, Robert, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Huntington, Daniel, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Inman, Henry, 1837, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kane, Philip Schuyler, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lambdin, James R., 1858 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Leutze, Emanuel, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miller, William R., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Morse, Samuel F. B., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Neagle, John, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Peale, Rembrandt, 1839, 1853-1854, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Persico, Luigi, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pine, John, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Renault, John Francis, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sargent, John Singer, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sully, Thomas, 1825-1840 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Trumbull, John, 1816, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - West, Benjamin, 1783, 1808, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Wood, Joseph, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - List of Miniature Painters, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)